I want to start out by asking you to think back to when you were a kid,
أريد البدء معكم بالطلب منكم بأن تعودوا بالذاكرة إلى حين كنتم أطفالاً
playing with blocks.
تلعبون بالمكعبات.
As you figured out how to reach out and grasp,
بينما توصلتٌم إلى معرفة كيفية التواصل والفهم
pick them up and move them around,
والتقاط المكعبات تحريكها،
you were actually learning how to think and solve problems
أنتم بالحقيقة تتعلمون كيفية التفكير وحل المسائل
by understanding and manipulating spatial relationships.
عبر الفهم والتلاعب بالعلاقات المكانية.
Spatial reasoning is deeply connected
المنطق المكاني هو متصل بقوة
to how we understand a lot of the world around us.
بالكيفية التي نفهم الكثير من العالم حولنا.
So, as a computer scientist
لذلك، كعالم حاسوب
inspired by this utility of our interactions with physical objects --
ملهم بأداة التفاعل مع الأجسام المادية -
along with my adviser Pattie, and my collaborator Jeevan Kalanithi --
وبالتعاون مع مستشارة الدراسية باتي ومع شريكي جيفان كلنيثي --
I started to wonder -- what if when we used a computer,
بدأت أتساءل -- ماذا لو استعملنا الحاسوب
instead of having this one mouse cursor that was a like a digital fingertip
بدلاً من مؤشر الفأرة الوحيد الذي كان يشبه طرف الإصبع الرقمي
moving around a flat desktop,
يتحرك على سطح مكتب أملس،
what if we could reach in with both hands and grasp information physically,
ماذا لو استطعنا الوصول بكلتا اليدين والتقاط المعلومات ماديا
arranging it the way we wanted?
وترتيبها بالطريقة التي نريد؟
This question was so compelling that we decided to explore the answer,
السؤال كان محفز جداً لذلك قررنا إستكشاف الجواب ،
by building Siftables.
عبر بناء سفتبلس.
In a nutshell, a Siftable is an interactive computer
بإختصار،كل سفتبلس هو كمبيوتر تفاعلي
the size of a cookie.
بحجم كعكة
They're able to be moved around by hand,
وبئستطاعتك تحريكها بواسطة اليد،
they can sense each other, they can sense their motion,
كذلك يمكنها استشعار بعضها، ويمكنها أيضاً استشعار حركتها،
and they have a screen and a wireless radio.
ولديها أيضاً شاشة، وراديو لاسلكي.
Most importantly, they're physical,
والأهم من كل هذا، انها مادية
so like the blocks, you can move them just by reaching out and grasping.
لذلك هي كالمكعبات ، يمكنك تحريكها بالوصول إليها والتقطها.
And Siftables are an example of a new ecosystem
وسفتبلس مثال على الأنظمة الإيكولوجية جديدة
of tools for manipulating digital information.
من الأدوات للتلاعب بالمعلومات الرقمية.
And as these tools become more physical,
ولأن هذه الأدوات أصبحت أكثر مادية ،
more aware of their motion, aware of each other,
وأكثر إدراكا لحركتها ، ولبعضها البعض،
and aware of the nuance of how we move them,
وإدراكها للفارق البسيط لكيفية نقلنا لها ،
we can start to explore some new and fun interaction styles.
أصبح بإمكاننا إستكشاف بعض أنماط التفاعل الجديدة والممتعة.
So, I'm going to start with some simple examples.
لذلك، سوف أبدأ ببعض الأمثلة البسيطة ،
This Siftable is configured to show video,
هذه السفتبله معدة لعرض الفيديو،
and if I tilt it in one direction, it'll roll the video this way;
وإذا أملتها بإتجاه واحد، سوف يتدحرج الفيديو بهذه الطريقة،
if I tilt it the other way it rolls it backwards.
وإذا أملتها بالإتجاه الأخر، سوف يتدحرج الفيديو بالمقلوب.
And these interactive portraits are aware of each other.
وهذه الصور التفاعلية مدركة كل منها للآخر.
So if I put them next to each other, they get interested.
لذلك إذا وضعتهم بجانب بعضهم، سوف يمسون مهتمين.
If they get surrounded, they notice that too,
وإذا حوصروا ،يمكنهم ملاحظة ذلك ايضا،
they might get a little flustered.
ويمكن أن ينزعجوا بعض الشيء.
And they can also sense their motion and tilt.
ويمكنهم أيضاً الإحساس بحركتهم وميلانهم.
One of the interesting implications on interaction, we started to realize,
وواحد من التداعيات الملفتة على التفاعل، التي بدأنا ندركها،
was that we could use everyday gestures on data,
هي أنه بإمكاننا إستعمال الحركات اليومية على المعلومات،
like pouring a color the way we might pour a liquid.
مثل سكب لون بالطريقة ذاتها التي نسكب فيها السوائل.
So in this case, we've got three Siftables configured to be paint buckets
وفي هذه الحالة، لدينا ثلاثة سفتبلس تمت تهيئتها لتكون أوعية طلاء
and I can use them to pour color into that central one,
وباستطاعتي استعمالها لسكب الطلاء بالسفتبل المركزي.
where they get mixed.
حيث يمكن أن يختلطوا.
If we overshoot, we can pour a little bit back.
وإذا أسرفنا، يمكننا إعادة سكب القليل.
There are also some neat possibilities for education,
وكذلك هناك بعض الإمكانيات النظيفة للتعليم،
like language, math and logic games
كللغة والرياضيات وألعاب المنطق
where we want to give people the ability to try things quickly,
حيث نريد إعطاء الناس إمكانية تجربة الأشياء بسرعة،
and view the results immediately.
وعرض النتائج بسرعة.
So here I'm --
لذلك ها أنا--
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This is a Fibonacci sequence that I'm making with a simple equation program.
وهذا هو تسلسل فيبونتشي الذي اصممه الأن بواسطة برنامج المعادلة البسيط.
Here we have a word game that's kind of like a mash-up between Scrabble and Boggle.
وهنا لدينا لعبة الكلمات الذي هو مثل نوع مزج بين الخربشة و التحير.
Basically, in every round
ببساطة، في كل دورة
you get a randomly assigned letter on each Siftable,
تحصل على حرف عشوائي على كل سفتبل،
and as you try to make words it checks against a dictionary.
وبينما أنت تجرب الكلمات سوف تقوم بالمقارنة مع القاموس.
Then, after about 30 seconds, it reshuffles,
وبعدها، بحوالي ٣٠ ثانية سوف تقوم بالتعديل،
and you have a new set of letters and new possibilities to try.
وعندها سوف يكون لديك مجموعة جديدة من الأحرف و إحتمالات جديدة للتجربة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكراً.
So these are some kids that came on a field trip to the Media Lab,
هنا بعض الأطفال الذين اتوا بزيارة ميدانية إلى "Media Lab" ،
and I managed to get them to try it out, and shoot a video.
وتمكنت من جعلهم يجربوها، وقمت بتصوير هذا الفيديو.
They really loved it.
وقد أحبوها فعلاً.
And, one of the interesting things about this kind of application
وبعض الأشياء المدهشة في هذا النوع من التطبيقات.
is that you don't have to give people many instructions.
هو أنه لست بحاجة لإعطاء الناس العديد من الإرشادات.
All you have to say is, "Make words,"
كل ما هو بحاجة لقوله هو، " ألف كلمات"،
and they know exactly what to do.
ولسوف يعلمون بالتحديد ماذا يفعلون.
So here's another few people trying it out.
وهنا مجموعة أخرى من الأشخاص يجربونها.
That's our youngest beta tester, down there on the right.
وهنا أصغر مجرب للنسخة بتا، هنالك في أسفل أقصى اليمين.
Turns out, all he wanted to do was to stack the Siftables up.
تبين إن كل ما يريد عمله هو تكديس السفتبلس فوق بعضها البعض.
So to him, they were just blocks.
لذلك، فهي بالنسبة له ليست إلى مكعبات.
Now, this is an interactive cartoon application.
الأن، هذا برنامج كرتون تفاعلي.
And we wanted to build a learning tool for language learners.
وأردنا بهذا بناء أداة تعليمية لمتعلمي اللغات.
And this is Felix, actually.
وفي الواقع، هذا هو "فليكس" .
And he can bring new characters into the scene,
وبإستطاعته أحضار أحرف جديدة إلى المشهد.
just by lifting the Siftables off the table that have that character shown on them.
فقط عبر رفع السفتبلس من على الطاولة التي يوجد عليها الأحرف المعروضة.
Here, he's bringing the sun out.
هنا، هو يحضر الشمس خارجاً.
Video: The sun is rising.
فيديو : الشمس تشرق.
David Merrill: Now he's brought a tractor into the scene.
دافيد مريل: الأن قام بإحضار جرار إلى المشهد.
Video: The orange tractor.
فيديو: الجرار البرتقالي.
Good job! Yeah!
عمل جيد! نعم!
DM: So by shaking the Siftables and putting them next to each other
عبر هز السفتبلس وبعد ذلك وضعها بجانب بعضها البعض.
he can make the characters interact --
وكذلك بإستطاعته جعل الأحرف تتفاعل.
Video: Woof!
فيديو : النسيج!
DM: inventing his own narrative.
د.م: يخترع سرده الخاص
Video: Hello!
فيديو : مرحبا!
DM: It's an open-ended story,
د.م: هي قصة غير محدودة النهاية،
and he gets to decide how it unfolds.
وهو يقرر كيفية سردها.
Video: Fly away, cat.
فيديو: اذهبي بعيدا أيتها القطة.
DM: So, the last example I have time to show you today
د.م: إذاً أخر مثل سؤبين اليكم اليوم
is a music sequencing and live performance tool
هو أداة للتسلسل موسيقي وقياس الأداء
that we've built recently,
التي قمنا ببنائها مؤخراً،
in which Siftables act as sounds
والتي تكون فيها سفتبلس كأصوات
like lead, bass and drums.
مثل الأحادي، والبص والطبول.
Each of these has four different variations,
وكلٍ من هذه لديها ثلاثة أنواع،
you get to choose which one you want to use.
ويعود لديك الخيار لإنتقاء أياً تريد الإستعمال.
And you can inject these sounds into a sequence
وبإمكانك ضخ هذه الأصوات في أي تسلسل
that you can assemble into the pattern that you want.
والتي بإستطاعاتك تجميعها في التكوين الذي تريد.
And you inject it by just bumping up the sound Siftable against a sequence Siftable.
وتقوم بضخها فقط عبر ضرب سفتبل واحد بتسلسل سفتبلس.
There are effects that you can control live, like reverb and filter.
هناك آثار يمكنك السيطرة عليها مباشرة وبواقعية ، مثل التردد والفلتر.
You attach it to a particular sound and then tilt to adjust it.
ويمكنك وصلها مع صوت محدد وبعد ذلك التحريك لتحسينها.
And then, overall effects like tempo and volume
وبعد ذلك التأثيرات المجملة كالوتير والصوت.
that apply to the entire sequence.
والتي يمكن تطبيقها على التسلسل بأكمله.
So let's have a look.
لذلك دعونا نلقي نظرة.
Video: (Music)
فيديو : (موسيقى)
DM: We'll start by putting a lead
د.م: سوف نبدأ بوضع الأحادي
into two sequence Siftables, arrange them into a series,
في تسلسل، بعدها نرتبها في سلسلة،
extend it, add a little more lead.
نوسعها، ونزيد عليها القليل من الأحادي.
Now I put a bass line in.
الأن ازيد القليل من الباص إليها.
Video: (Music)
فيديو : (موسيقى)
DM: Now I'll put some percussion in.
د.م: والآن سوف يضع بعض القرع فيها.
DM: And now I'll attach the filter to the drums, so I can control the effect live.
د.م:الأن سوف أوصل الفلتر الى الطبول حتى استطيع التحكم بالأثر فيها بالوقت الحقيقي.
Video: (Music)
فيديو : (موسيقى)
DM: I can speed up the whole sequence
وأستطيع أن أسرع كل التسلسل.
by tilting the tempo one way or the other.
عبر تحريك الوتير في جهة أو أخرى.
Video: (Music)
فيديو : (موسيقى)
DM: And now I'll attach the filter to the bass for some more expression.
د.م: والآن سوف نعلق الفلتر إلى الباص لمزيد من التعبير.
DM: I can rearrange the sequence while it plays.
د.م: وأستطيع إعادة ترتيب السلسلة بينما هي دائرة.
So I don't have to plan it out in advance, but I can improvise,
لذا ليس لدي خطة لها مسبقا ، ولكن يمكنني أن الارتجال ،
making it longer or shorter as I go.
عبر جعلها أطول أو أكثر حسب حركتي.
And now, finally, I can fade the whole sequence out
و أخيرا استطيع أن الاشي كل التسلسل خارجاً.
using the volume Siftable, tilted to the left.
بواسطة إستخدام سفتبل الصوت عبر تحريكها إلى اليسار.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
So, as you can see,
لذلك كما ترون،
my passion is for making new human-computer interfaces
لذلك ولهي هو إختراع وسائط الإنسان-الحاسوب الجديدة
that are a better match to the ways our brains and bodies work.
التي هي مطابقة أكثر للطريقة التي يعمل بها دماغنا وجسدنا.
And today, I had time to show you one point in this new design space,
وليوم عرضت لكم نقطة في هذا التصميم المجالي الجديد.
and a few of the possibilities that we're working to bring out of the laboratory.
وقلل من الأشياء الممكنة التي نعمل الى اخرجها من المختبر.
So the thought I want to leave you with
لذلك ارتأيت أن أترككم مع
is that we're on the cusp of this new generation of tools
اننا على اعتاب جيل جديد من الأدوات.
for interacting with digital media
للتفاعل مع التطبيقات الرقمية،
that are going to bring information into our world
التي تعمل على جلب المعلومات إلى عالمنا
on our terms.
بمفاهيمنا الخاصة.
Thank you very much.
شكراً لكم جزيلاً.
I look forward to talking with all of you.
اني اتطلع للتحدث معكم جميعاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)